Guide to the Harold Barger papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Harold Barger Papers,
1946-1981
Barger, Harold 1907-.
4.5 linear ft. (9 document boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
MS#0069
5801327
Biographical Note
Harold Barger, 1907-1989 was an educator and economist. He was Professor of economics at Columbia University from 1939 to 1989.
Scope and Content
The general correspondence in the collection deals with Barger's dissertation and writings in the area of economics. Of note are letters from John Maynard Keynes, Dennis Robertson, and Wesley C. Mitchell; correspondence with chairman and other departmental faculty members concerning research and other departmental activities; and correspondence with foreign scholars concerning research.
Included with the manuscript material are manuscripts of Myrdal's "Prisbildningsproblemet och foranderligheten" and "Capital Consumption" by F.A. Hayek. Manuscripts by Barger include comments from editors and reviewers, his Cambridge essays, and other subjects such as, "Increase of Capital" and "Speculation."
His work on various university committees includes minutes from meetings, offices held, involvement with students. There are also some subject files, including research materials from a visiting Professorship in Venezuela, as well as the economic conditions of the nation during his stay; programs from conferences attended as well as papers he presented or were of interest to him; a speech that he presented at Washington State University; and some personal photographs.
Course related materials include course syllabi and examinations. His research notes include economic indicators for Europe, United States, some individual states, and developing nations. There are general research notes, and his own economic theories as well as his research on the history of Euro/American economic theory. The printed materials consist of articles and editorial letters written by Barger as well as reprints related to the field of economics, many inscribed by their respective authors.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 7 series:
Series I: Correspondence and Subject Files
Series II: Columbia Committees and Other University Activities
Series III: Manuscripts by Barger with editorial comments
Series IV: Manuscripts by Barger and by Others
Series V: Teaching
Series VI: Research Files
Series VII: Printed Materials
Subjects
Columbia University.--Dept. of Economics.; Columbia University--Faculty.; Barger, Harold--1907-.; Hayek, Friedrich A. von (Friedrich August), 1899-1992.; Keynes, John Maynard, 1883-1946.; Mitchell, Wesley C. (Wesley Clair), 1874-1948.; Myrdal, Gunnar, 1898-1987.; Robertson, Dennis Holme, Sir, 1890-1963.; Banks and banking.; Business cycles.; Economics.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
[source of acquisition] Gift, Purchase, etc. date accn number
- Series I: Correspondence and Subject Files
  - Subseries I.1: Cataloged Correspondence
    - A-Z (Box l)
  - Subseries I.2: General Correspondence (1956-81)
    - Correspondence with Foreign Scholars, 1965-81 (Box 1)
    - Departmental Correspondence, 1950-75 (Box 1)
    - Visiting Professorship with related material (Box 1)
    - Conferences (Box 1)
    - Speech (Box 1)
- Series II: Columbia Committees and Other University Activities
  - A-F (Box 1)
  - G-Z (Box 2)
- Series III: Manuscripts by Barger with editorial comments
  - Various manuscripts (Box 3)
- Series IV: Manuscripts by Barger and by Others
  - Various manuscripts (Box 4)
- Series V: Teaching
  - Teaching Aids (Box 5)
  - Syllabi and Examinations (Box 5)
- Series VI: Research Files
  - Europe, pt. 1, 1950-1971 (Box 5)
  - Europe, pt. 2, 1950-71 (Box 6)
  - Europe, pt. 3, 1950-71 (Box 7)
  - United States, 1950-68 (Box 7)
  - Various states, 1879, 1905 (Box 7)
  - Developing nations, 1946-49 (Box 7)
  - General Research Notes and Economic Theory, pt. 1 (Box 8)
  - General Research Notes and Economic Theory, pt. 2 (Box 9)
  - History of Economic Thought (Box 10)
- Series VII: Printed Materials
  - Clippings and Reprints (Box 11-12)